# **JUSTIN T. VAN DIJK**

**W** www.mappingdutchman.com **o** 0000-0001-5496-425X

Updated April 29, 2020

#### **Profile**

Human Geographer. Data scientist. Teacher. Interested in urban analytics, geo-demographics, urban transport, spatial inequalities, and big data applications in scarce data environments. Extensive experience in the domain of Geographic Information Systems, urban studies, and transport research. Possesses a wide skill set in the field of advanced spatial analysis, including experience with Python programming, R scripting, and PostgreSQL/PostGIS.

# **Present appointment**

2018 - Present Postdoctoral research associate, University College London

Department of Geography. Geospatial Analytics and Computing Research Group. Working on the analysis and visualisation of big spatial population data sets; both historic and contemporary.

### **Previous appointments**

2014 - 2017 **Junior lecturer** (part-time), Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics. Tasks included thesis supervision of BSc (Honours) students and teaching the post-graduate course *Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis*.

*2013* **Junior lecturer**, Utrecht University

Department of Human Geography and Planning. Tasks included thesis supervision of BSc students and teaching various undergraduate courses on Geographic Information Systems Human Geography and Planning.

2012 **Teaching assistant**, Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics. Assistant in the course *Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis*.

2009 - 2012 **Teaching assistant**, Utrecht University

Department of Human Geography and Planning. Assistant in the courses *Introduction to GIS, Transport Geography*, and *Advanced GIS*.

### **Education**

2014 - 2017 **Doctor of Philosophy**, Stellenbosch University

Transport Economics. Thesis: Designing Travel Behaviour Change interventions: A spatiotemporal perspective.

2011 - 2013 Master of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0. Cum Laude.

Human Geography and Planning. Thesis: Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa.

2007 - 2011 Bachelor of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0.

Human Geography and Planning. Thesis: Contemporary Orientalism? Representations of Islam and Muslims in the Dutch Press: a content analysis of 'De Volkskrant' and 'De Telegraaf', 2001-2010.

# **Refereed publications: International journals**

- 1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Longley, P. A., 2020, Interactive display of surname distributions in historic and contemporary Great Britain. *Journal of Maps* 169(1): 68-76. doi: 10.1080/17445647. 2020.1746418
- 2. Kandt, J., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A., 2020, Family name origins and inter-generational demographic change in Great Britain. *Annals of the American Association of Geographers*. Advance Online Publication. doi: 10.1080/24694452.2020.1717328
- 3. Engin, Z., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lan, T., Longley, P. A., Treleaven, P., Batty, M., and Penn, A., 2019, Data-driven urban management: Mapping the landscape. *Journal of Urban Management*. Advance Online Publication. doi: 10.1016/j.jum.2019.12.001
- 4. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, 2018, Identifying activity-travel points from GPS-data with multiple moving windows. *Computers, Environment and Urban System* 70: 84-101. doi: 10.1016/j.compenv urbsys.2018.02.004
- 5. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Krygsman, S.C., 2017, Using GPS-based activity spaces and opportunity indicators for travel behaviour analysis. *Journal of Urban Technology* 25(2): 105-124. doi: 10.1080/19475683.2017.1340340
- 6. **Van Dijk, J. T.** and De Jong, T. 2017, Post-processing GPS tracks in reconstructing travelled routes in a GIS-environment: Network subset selection and attribute adjustment. *Annals of GIS* 23(3): 203-217. doi: 10.1080/10630732.2017.1400814
- 7. Idahosa, L. O. and **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, 2015, Freedom for whom in South Africa? Inequality, unemployment and the elderly. *Development* 58(1): 96-102. doi: 10.1057/dev.2015.18

8. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Krygsman, S. C., and De Jong, T., 2015, Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa. *Journal of Transport and Land use* 8(3): 95-114. doi: 10.5198/jtlu.2015.555

### **Manuscripts under consideration**

1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., Using linked consumer registers to estimate internal migration in the United Kingdom. *Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series A (Statistics in Society)*. Under review.

### Manuscripts in preparation

1. **Van Dijk, J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., Consumer data perspectives upon residential mobility in the UK housing market.

# **Book chapters**

- 1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., Using linked consumer and administrative data to model demographic changes in London's city fringe. In: Clarke, G., Birkin, M., and Stimson, B. (Eds.), *Applications of Big Data in geography and planning*. Cheltenham: Edward Elgar Publishing Ltd. Forthcoming.
- 2. Wolfensberger M., Dekker, M., **Van Dijk, J. T.**, Zubizarreta, J., Hait, C., Mann, C., and Lucas, C., 2013, Learning as salon: Honors International Collaboration. In: Mulvaney, M. K. and Klein, K. (Eds.), *Preparing Tomorrow's Global Leaders: Honors International Education*, pp. 75-84. Lincoln: National Collegiate Honors Council. NCHC Monograph Series.

# **Conference proceedings**

- 1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Longley, P. A., 2020, Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names. In: Westerholt, R. and Mocnick, F.-B. (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science (PLATIAL'19*). Warwick: Warwick University. 23-31. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.3628863
- 2. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., Lan, T., and Longley, P. A., 2019, Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.
- 3. Lan, T., Lansley, G., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A., 2019, Geocoding historical census records in England and Wales. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.
- 4. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Krygsman, S. C., 2016, Mobile technologies for data collection in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of mobility research. #CelebrateGeography: Proceedings of the 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers (SSAG 2016). Stellenbosch: SunMedia. 180-189.

5. **Van Dijk, J. T.** and Krygsman, S. C., 2015, Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study. *Proceedings of the 34th Southern African Transport Conference (SATC 2015). Pretoria: Southern Africa Transport Conference*. 448-460.

# **Professional publications**

1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and De Jong, T., 2010, Medische voorzieningen in kaart. Bereikbaarheid medische voorzieningen in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng en Sekhukhune [Accessibility of Medical services in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng and Sekhukhune]. *Geografie* 19 (5): 18-20.

#### **Books**

1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, 2017, Designing Travel Behaviour Change Interventions: a spatiotemporal perspective [dissertation]. Stellenbosch: Stellenbosch University. Persistent URL: http://hdl.handle.net/10019.1/102809

#### **Grants**

2020	Frank Carter Travel Fund, University College London £ 550
2015 - 2017	NRF-DST innovation scholarship, National Research Foundation and Department of Science and Technology ZAR 330,000
2016	Postgraduate travel grant, National Research Foundation ZAR 24,222
2015 - 2016	Stellenbosch merit bursary, Stellenbosch University <b>ZAR 50,000</b>
2014 - 2016	Scholarship award for full-time doctoral studies, Stellenbosch University <b>ZAR 390,000</b>

### Papers presented at international conferences

- 1. "Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names". 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science. *Warwick, United Kingdom, September 5 September 6, 2019.*
- 2. "Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change". 27th Conference of GIS Research UK. *Newcastle, United Kingdom, April 23 April 26, 2019.*
- 3. "Mobile data collection techniques in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of transport research". 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers. *Stellenbosch, South Africa, September 25 September 25, 2016.*

- 4. "Designing a Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change Intervention: Smartphones and Space-Time Accessibility Analysis". Mobile Tartu 2016. *Tartu, Estonia, June 29 – July 1, 2016*.
- 5. "Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study". 34th Southern African Transport Conference. *Pretoria, South Africa, 6 July July 9, 2015.*
- 6. "Twenty years of Freedom: The role of the Old Persons Grant in addressing unemployment and inequality in a young democracy". 12th Development Dialogue "Rethinking Democracy". *The Hague, the Netherlands, October 16 October 17, 2014.*
- 7. "Towards spatial justice: The spatial Equity Effects of a Toll Road in Cape Town, South Africa". World Symposium on Transport and Land Use. *Delft, the Netherlands, June 24 June 27, 2014.*

#### **Guest lectures and invited research seminars**

- 1. "What's in a name? Storing surname geographies for both visualisation and analysis". Guest lecture Graduate School Economic and Management Sciences. *Stellenbosch University, South Africa, March 8, 2019.*
- 2. "What's in a name? Storing surname geographies for both visualisation and analysis". Geo+Data London (AGI/CDRC event). *University College London, United Kingdom, December 4, 2018.*
- 3. "Using GPS-enabled smartphones for Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change interventions". Guest lecture Utrecht University Summer School on "GPS data analysis". *Utrecht University, the Netherlands, July 12, 2017.*
- 4. "GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the course "Introduction to GIS". *Utrecht University, the Netherlands, February 18, 2016.*
- 5. "GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the course "Introduction to GIS". *Utrecht University, the Netherlands, November 25, 2015.*

### **Enabling roles**

2019 - 2020 Undergraduate dissertation supervision

Co-supervisor undergraduate dissertation. Institute of Education, University College London.

2019 "Technical Tuesdays" seminar series

Co-organiser and speaker in this weekly Seminar Series on methods and techniques for quantitative researchers. GitHub: https://github.com/jtvandijk/TechnicalTuesdays

2019 Nuffield Research Placement supervision

Supervision of first-generation prospective university student.

2014 - 2015 Social Sciences for Development conference

Member of the local organising committee at Stellenbosch University for the

2015 conference.

# Web development

2019 - Present Gamble Aware

Data analysis and visualisations on the geographical distribution of supply

and demand for treatment and support for problematic gamblers.

2018 - Present GBNames website

Website development. GBNames explores the spread of family names across Great Britain, using historic censuses and recent consumer registers, and links surnames to consumer data statistics. The latest version of the

website is accessible through: gbnames.mappingdutchman.com

# **External projects**

2019 Greater London Authority

Preparation of selected data products on ethnicity, population churn,

migration, and social mobility for the Greater London Authority.

2016 – 2017 Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator

Data analysis using well-known statistical techniques as well as more advanced machine learning classifiers for Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator to better understand, and possibly predict, successful job

placements.

2016 - 2017 Human Sciences Research Council

Contributions project proposal for funding the establishment of a nationally

representative cell phone panel of South Africans.

2009 AfriScope

Contributions to a study on the accessibility of government services in the Integrated Sustainable Rural Development (ISRD) Nodes in South Africa.

**Review** 

2020 Computers, Environment, and Urban Systems

Journal of Transport Geography

Transactions in GIS

2019 Transactions in GIS

Journal of Transport Geography

The Israel Science Foundation (Grant review)

Journal of Traffic and Transportation Engineering

2018 Journal of Transport Geography

Computers, Environment, and Urban Systems

2016 Area Development and Policy2015 Journal of Transport and Land Use

### Core technical skills

Geographic Information Systems R, Python, Q-GIS, ArcGIS

Data processing R, Python, Bash, GNU Parallel

Data analysisR, PythonData visualisationggplotProject managementGit, GitHubWeb mappingLeaflet.js

Web development HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Django

Database management PostgreSQL

Typesetting LaTeX

# **Language proficiency**

Dutch Native proficiency

English Full professional proficiency isiXhosa Basic conversational proficiency

### References

Professor Paul Longley

Professor of Geographic Information Science, University College London **E** p.longley@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 (0) 20 7679 0500

Professor James Cheshire

Professor of Geographic Information and Cartography, University College London

**E** james.cheshire@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 (0) 20 7679 0513

Dr Neil Rankin

Extraordinary Associate Professor Economics, Stellenbosch University

Data scientist, Predictive Insights

**E** neil@predictiveinsights.net **T** +27 (0) 21 808 2678